For us, free research is important
För oss är den fria forskningen viktig
Free basic research is driven by the researcher's curiosity and interest in looking for new knowledge.
Fri grundforskning drivs av forskarens nyfikenhet och intresse att söka efter ny kunskap.
Many discoveries that we see as obvious have come out of free research:
Många upptäckter som vi ser som självklara har kommit ur den fria forskningen:
Penicillin
Penicillin
Microwave oven
Microvågsugn
Lithium batteries
Litiumbatterier
Solar panels
Solpaneler
X -ray
Röntgen
The greenhouse effect
Växthuseffekten
The discoveries have been made from curiosity, randomness or research that did not become as they first thought.
Upptäckterna har gjorts av nyfikenhet, slump eller forskning som inte blev som man först tänkt.
Some of them have received the Nobel Prize.
Några av dem har fått Nobelpris.
The graph, DNA, LED lamp and the scissors
Grafen, DNA, LED-lampa och gensaxen
Free research gives us new knowledge beyond today's horizon and can open entirely new areas of knowledge.
Den fria forskningen ger oss ny kunskap bortom dagens horisont och kan öppna helt nya kunskapsområden.
It gives us important knowledge and preparedness to meet our societal challenges.
Den ger oss viktig kunskap och beredskap för att möta våra samhällsutmaningar.
Therefore, the majority of the Swedish Research Council's money goes to projects where the researchers themselves formulated their research idea.
Därför går majoriteten av Vetenskapsrådets pengar till projekt där forskarna själva formulerat sin forskningsidé.
The Swedish Research Council - research for a wiser world
Vetenskapsrådet - forskning för en klokare värld